<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
  #%L
  ESB :: Release Notes
  %%
  Copyright (C) 2011 Talend Inc.
  %%
	This documentation is provided under the terms of the Creative Commons Public License (CCPL).
	For more information about what you can and cannot do with this documentation in accordance with the
	CCPL, please read: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/
  #L%
  -->

<!DOCTYPE book>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Release Notes for Talend ESB Standard Edition(SE)</title>
        <subtitle>Version 4.0</subtitle>
                <pubdate>April 2011</pubdate>
        <author>
            <orgname>Talend Corporation</orgname>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>2011</year>
            <holder>Talend Corporation</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Copyleft</title>
            <para>
				This documentation is provided under the terms of the Creative Commons Public License (CCPL).
				For more information about what you can and cannot do with this documentation in accordance with the
				CCPL, please read: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Notices</title>
            <para>
                Talend, Talend ESB, Talend Integration Factory, and Talend Service Factory are trademarks of Talend, Inc.
            </para>
            <para>
                Apache CXF, CXF, Apache Karaf, Karaf, Apache Camel, Camel, Apache Maven, and Maven are trademarks of The Apache Foundation.
            </para>
            <para>
                Eclipse Equinox is a trademark of the Eclipse Foundation.
            </para>
            <para>
                All other brands, product names, company names, trademarks and service marks are the properties of their respective owners.
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
    </info>
    <chapter>

<title>Installation and Documentation Packages</title>
<para>
Talend ESB SE is delivered as two separate packages, one containing the software and the other containing the documentation and examples. It is recommended that both packages be extracted to a common directory location.
<para>Binary distribution:</para>
<para><code>talend-esb-4.0.[tar.gz|zip]</code></para> 
<para>Documentation and Examples:</para>
<para><code>talend-esb-4.0-doc.[tar.gz|zip]</code></para> 
</para>


<para><emphasis role="strong">Talend ESB 4.0</emphasis></para>
<para>
<para>The following outlines the installation directory structure for both packages.</para>

<para>directory: <emphasis role="strong">talend-esb-4.0/ </emphasis></para>
</para>
<para>
<informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="20*" />
		<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="80*" />  
        <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Subdirectory</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Description</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>add-ons/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries required for the Talend ESB Service Locator and Monitoring features
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>bin/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Command line tools/shell scripts (e.g. code generation)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>container/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Pre-configured OSGi container based on Eclipse Equinox and Apache Karaf
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>docs/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                 API documentation for Apache CXF in Javadoc format
              </entry>
            </row>  
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>etc/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Various configuration files for Apache CXF
              </entry>
            </row>            
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>lib/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries required for using Talend ESB (see WHICH_JARS for more details)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>licenses/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                 License documents for the third party components included in Talend ESB
              </entry>
            </row>                 
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>modules/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries that comprise Apache CXF (used to create lightweight distributions of CXF if not all functionality is required)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>samples/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The standard example source code that comes with Apache CXF and Apache Camel
              </entry>
            </row>   
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>zookeeper/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Apache ZooKeeper which is required for the Talend ESB Service Locator feature
              </entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable> 
</para>

 

<para><emphasis role="strong">Talend ESB 4.0 (Documentation)</emphasis></para>
<para>directory: <emphasis role="strong">talend-esb-4.0-doc/</emphasis></para>
<para>
<informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="20*" />
		<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="80*" />  
        <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Subdirectory</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Description</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>docs/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Manuals and User Guides for Talend ESB in PDF format
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>examples/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Extended, documented examples for Talend ESB
              </entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable> 
</para>


</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>System Requirements</title>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
Talend ESB does not have any specific hardware requirements, beyond the recommended hardware requirements for the supporting application server or Java runtime environment.
</section>

<section>
<title>Software Requirements</title>
<para>
Talend ESB is supported on the following operating systems:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Microsoft Windows</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        Windows XP (>= Service Pack 2), Windows Vista, Windows 7 
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        Windows Server 2003 (>= Service Pack 2), Windows Server 2008 or higher
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para> 


<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Linux</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    RHEL 5.4 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    SUSE 10 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    CentOS 5.4 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    Ubuntu 10 or higher 
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>   
</para>
 
<para><emphasis role="strong">Apple MacOS</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    10.5 or higher
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

<para>
Talend ESB is supported on the following Appserver and Java runtime environments:
</para>
<!-- <para>-->
<para><emphasis role="strong">Java Virtual Machine</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    ORACLE JRE / JDK 6 (Update 6 or higher) 
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

<para><emphasis role="strong">Application Server</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    OSGi Runtime (Eclipse Equinox 3.6 / Apache Karaf 2.2.0 - included in this delivery)
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    Apache Tomcat 6.0.x and 7.0.x
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

</section>



</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Highlighted Features, Changes and Fixes</title>

<para>Talend ESB SE includes both the Talend Service Factory 2.4.0 and Talend Integration Factory 2.7.1 distributions.</para>
<para>In additional, Talend ESB SE 4.0 includes the following features:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Service Locator</listitem>
<listitem>Service Activity Monitoring(SAM)</listitem>
<listitem>"Car Rental" demo application</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section>
<title>Highlighted Features</title>
<section>
<title>Service Locator</title>
<para>The Service Locator in the add-ons directory is a service that provides its consumers with a mechanism to discover service endpoints at 
run time. The Service Locator consists of two parts:  An Endpoint repository and a CXF feature used to configure the use of the Service Locator 
from both the provider and consumer sides. Like any standard CXF feature, the ServiceLocator Feature is configured separately for the service 
provider and service consumer. The provider side Locator Feature extension registers and deregisters service endpoints in the endpoint 
repository when the provider becomes available or unavailable. The consumer side Locator Feature extension transparently retrieves 
service endpoint addresses from the endpoint repository when a service call to a provider is to be made.
</para>
<para>For more information how to install and configure the Service Locator see the Service Locator Installation Manual (docs/SLInstallationManual.pdf) and the
Service Locator Configuration Manual (docs/SLConfigurationManual.pdf).</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Service Activity Monitoring (SAM)</title>
<para>The Service Activity Monitoring (SAM) in the add-ons directory allows to log / monitor service calls done with the Apache CXF Framework. 
Typical use cases are usage statistics, fault monitoring and correlation of message across multiple services. SAM consists of two parts: 1. Agent (sam-agent) and 2. Monitoring Server (sam-server). 
The Agent creates events out of the requests and replies on service consumer and provider side. The events are first collected 
locally and then sent to the monitoring server periodically to not disturb the normal message flow. The Monitoring Server receives events 
from the Agent, optionally filters/handlers events and stores them into a Database.</para>
<para>For more information about the Service Activity Monitoring feature see the Service Activity Monitoring User Guide (docs/SAMUserGuide.pdf).</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Car Rental Demo</title>
<para>The Car Rental Demo is a simplified real-world example, using
the domain of car rental companies to demonstrate the use of Talend
ESB for developing and deploying services. It comes with a detailed 
Getting Started Guide that step by step describes how to compile the
demo, deploy it into the Talend ESB Runtime OSGi container and then
activate it.
The demo also shows how to enable the Service Locator Component for the
services deployed in the demo, and how Service Activity Monitoring can be
enabled.
</para>
<para>For more information about the Car Rental Demo see the Getting Started Guide (docs/GettingStartedGuide.pdf).</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Talend Service Factory 2.4.0</title>
<para>
Talend ESB contains the Talend Service Factory 2.4.0 with a lot of new features.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
	LogBrowser console
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
	Transformation feature provides for a fast and effective way to transform inbound and/or outbound XML messages.
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    JiBX databinding
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
	Faster startup and reduced spring configuration. The Spring support has been redone to be based on the ExtensionManagerBus. This results in much faster startup. It also means that all of the imports of META-INF/cxf/cxf-extension-*.xml are no longer needed.
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    WSS4J has been updated from 1.5.x to 1.6. Some notable new features for CXF users include: 
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
    SAML2 support: WSS4J 1.6 includes full support for creating, manipulating and parsing SAML2 assertions, via the Opensaml2 library.
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
	Performance work: A general code-rewrite has been done with a focus on improving performance.
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	Support for Crypto trust-stores: WSS4J 1.6 separates the concept of keystore and truststores.
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    WS-SecurityPolicy support for SAML tokens.
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
	Initial Apache Aries Blueprint support. This is a work in progress, but many of the Spring namespace handlers that are used with Spring to start/create/configure clients and services now have Blueprint versions as well. See http://cxf.apache.org/schemas/blueprint/ for some of the schemas that have been ported to Blueprint.
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
<para>For more information about the Talend Service Factory see the Talend Service Factory User Guide (docs/TSFUsersGuide.pdf).</para>
<para  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
For more details please see: <link  xlink:href="http://cxf.apache.org/docs/24-migration-guide.html">Apache CXF 2.4 migration guide</link>. 
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Talend Integration Factory 2.7.1</title>
<para>
Talend ESB contains the Talend Integration Factory 2.7.1 with a lot of new features.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
	Added 4 new components: Context, Hazelcast Component, DNS and MyBatis 
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    Switched to using slf4j as the logger instead of commons logging 
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    Added support for MDC logging with Camel 
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    DSL improvements 
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
    Improvements for a few components like JMS, HTTP, File, Quartz 
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    Improvements of the test kit and Mock component 
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
	fixes and improvements related to using Camel in OSGi 
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>For more information about the Talend Integration Factory see the Talend Integration Factory User Guide (docs/TIFUsersGuide.pdf).</para>
<para xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
For more details please see the: <link  xlink:href="http://camel.apache.org/camel-270-release.html">Apache Camel 2.7.0 release notes</link> and the <link  xlink:href="http://camel.apache.org/camel-271-release.html">Apache Camel 2.7.1 release notes</link>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>Changes</title>
<para>
Not applicable.
</para>
</section>


<section><title>Fixed Bugs</title>
<para>
Not applicable.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Known Limitations</title>

<para><emphasis role="strong"> SAM Server is required to be deployed on Apache Tomcat container.</emphasis></para>
<para>In this release of the Talend ESB the Service Activity Management (SAM) Server is required to be deployed on Tomcat 6. 
In future versions of Talend ESB we will also support the deployment within the Talend ESB OSGi container. 
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Known Issues</title>
<para>
Not applicable..
</para>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Export Notice</title>
<para>
This distribution includes cryptographic software.  The country in which
you currently reside may have restrictions on the import, possession, use,
and/or re-export to another country, of encryption software.  BEFORE using
any encryption software, please check your country's laws, regulations and
policies concerning the import, possession, or use, and re-export of
encryption software, to see if this is permitted.  See
&lt;http://www.wassenaar.org/> for more information. 
</para>
<para>
The U.S. Government Department of Commerce, Bureau of Industry and Security
(BIS), has classified this software as Export Commodity Control Number
(ECCN) 5D002.C.1, which includes information security software using or
performing cryptographic functions with asymmetric algorithms.  The form
and manner of this Apache Software Foundation distribution makes it eligible
for export under the License Exception ENC Technology Software Unrestricted
(TSU) exception (see the BIS Export Administration Regulations, Section
740.13) for both object code and source code.
</para>
</chapter>

<chapter xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Reporting Defects and Issues</title>
<para>
For community technical support use the Talend
User's Forum at
<link  xlink:href="http://www.talendforge.org/forum/">Talend Forum - Talend ESB</link>. 
You can also look at the Open and Fixed issues provided in the Bug tracker 
<link  xlink:href="https://jira.sopera.de/secure/Dashboard.jspa">Talend Bug Tracker - Project: Talend ESB</link>
</para>
<para>
If you have a valid customer support contract for Talend ESB (SE/EE) 
with Talend you can access the Talend Online Helpdesk or you can
contact customer support by phone and e-mail as stated in your contracts.
</para>
<para>
Please provide the following information:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
Product and Version which you used (for example, Talend ESB 4.0 SE) 
</listitem><listitem>
Version of Java Platform JDK / JRE in use.
</listitem><listitem>
Log files
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Also, in order to ensure that the technical support team has sufficient information to
help you, describe at least the following in detail:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
your actions up to the point when the problem occurred
</listitem><listitem>
the results you expected
</listitem><listitem>
the ensuing results that differ from your expected results.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</chapter>


</book>