<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Release Notes for Talend ESB(SE)</title>
        <subtitle>Covers 4.0</subtitle>
                <pubdate>22 April 2011</pubdate>
        <author>
            <orgname>Talend Corporation</orgname>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>2011</year>
            <holder>Talend Corporation</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Copyleft</title>
            <para>
This documentation is provided under the terms of the Creative Commons Public License (CCPL).
For more information about what you can and cannot do with this documentation in accordance with the
CCPL, please read: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Notices</title>
            <para>
                Talend, Talend Integration Factory, and Talend Service Factory are trademarks of Talend, Inc.
            </para>
            <para>
                Apache CXF, CXF, Apache Karaf, Karaf, Apache Camel, Camel, Apache Maven, and Maven are trademarks of The Apache Foundation.
            </para>
            <para>
                Eclipse Equinox is a trademark of the Eclipse Foundation.
            </para>
            <para>
                All other brands, product names, company names, trademarks and service marks are the properties of their respective owners.
            </para>

        </legalnotice>
    </info>
    <chapter>

<title>Scope of Delivery</title>
<para>
Talend ESB SE 4.0 is delivered in two separate packages that should be extracted 
to the same file system location: 
<para><code>talend-esb-4.0.[tar.gz|zip]</code></para> 
which contains the software
<para><code>talend-esb-4.0-doc.[tar.gz|zip]</code></para> 
which contains the accompanying documentation and source code for examples.
</para>

<para>Here is an overview of the package contents:</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Talend ESB 4.0</emphasis></para>
<para>directory: <emphasis role="strong">talend-esb-4.0/ </emphasis></para>

<para>
<informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="20*" />
		<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="80*" />  
        <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Subdirectory</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Description</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>add-ons/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries required for the Talend ESB Service Locator and Monitoring features
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>bin/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Command line tools/shell scripts (e.g. code generation)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>container/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Pre-configured OSGi container based on Eclipse Equinox and Apache Karaf
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>docs/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                 API documentation for Apache CXF in Javadoc format
              </entry>
            </row>  
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>etc/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Various configuration files for Apache CXF
              </entry>
            </row>            
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>lib/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries required for using Talend ESB (see WHICH_JARS for more details)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>licenses/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                 License documents for the third party components included in Talend ESB
              </entry>
            </row>                 
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>modules/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Libraries that comprise Apache CXF (used to create lightweight distributions of CXF if not all functionality is required)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
               <code>samples/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The standard example source code that comes with Apache CXF and Apache Camel
              </entry>
            </row>   
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>zookeeper/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Apache ZooKeeper which is required for the Talend ESB Service Locator feature
              </entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable> 
</para>

 

<para><emphasis role="strong">Talend ESB 4.0 (Documentation)</emphasis></para>
<para>directory: <emphasis role="strong">talend-esb-4.0-doc/</emphasis></para>
<para>
<informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="20*" />
		<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="80*" />  
        <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Subdirectory</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Description</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>docs/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Manuals and User Guides for Talend ESB in PDF format
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <code>examples/</code>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Extended, documented examples for Talend ESB
              </entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable> 
</para>


</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>System Requirements</title>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
Talend ESB does not require any specific hardware besides the recommended 
hardware requirements specified for the use of the supported operating systems and application servers / runtime container. 
</section>

<section>
<title>Software Requirements</title>
<para>
Talend ESB is supported for the following software:
</para>
<para>Operating System:</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Microsoft Windows</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        Windows XP (>= Service Pack 2), Windows Vista, Windows 7 
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        Windows Server 2003 (>= Service Pack 2), Windows Server 2008 or higher
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para> 


<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Linux</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    RHEL 5.4 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    SUSE 10 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    CentOS 5.4 or higher
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    Ubuntu 10 or higher 
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>   
</para>
 
<para><emphasis role="strong">Apple MacOS</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    10.5 or higher
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

<para><emphasis role="strong">Java Virtual Machine</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    ORACLE JRE / JDK 6 (Update 6 or higher) 
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

<para><emphasis role="strong">Application Server</emphasis>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    OSGi Runtime (Eclipse Equinox / Apache Karaf - included in this delivery)
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    Tomcat 6.0.x
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</para>

</section>



</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New Features, Changes and Fixes</title>

<para>Talend ESB SE bundles Talend Service Factory 2.4.0 and Talend Integration Factory 2.7.1,
Service Locator, Service Activity Monitoring and a demo application
to a stable, production ready distribution based on the industry leading
open source frameworks Apache CXF and Apache Camel.</para> 
<para>
It includes Web Service support based on JAX-WS and enables simple and scalable
message based systems using well known Enterprise Integration Patterns.
The Service Locator maintains a repository of service endpoints which
can be used by Service Consumers to support loosely coupling, failover and load
balancing. Service Activity Monitoring allows to log and
monitor service calls. A documented Car Rental demo application illustrates
how to use these features.
</para>

<section>
<title>Highlighted Features</title>
<section>
<title>Service Locator</title>
<para>The Service Locator in the add-ons directory is a service that provides its consumers with a mechanism to discover service endpoints at 
run time. The Service Locator consists of two parts:  An Endpoint repository and a CXF feature used to configure the use of the Service Locator 
from both the provider and consumer sides. Like any standard CXF feature, the ServiceLocator Feature is configured separately for the service 
provider and service consumer. The provider side Locator Feature extension registers and deregisters service endpoints in the endpoint 
repository when the provider becomes available or unavailable. The consumer side Locator Feature extension transparently retrieves 
service endpoint addresses from the endpoint repository when a service call to a provider is to be made.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Service Activity Monitoring (SAM)</title>
The Service Activity Monitoring (SAM) in the add-ons directory allows to log / monitor service calls done with the Apache CXF Framework. 
Typical use cases are usage statistics and fault monitoring.  The solution consists of two parts: Agent (sam-agent) and Monitoring Server 
(sam-server). The Agent creates events out of the requests and replies on service consumer and provider side. The events are first collected 
locally and then sent to the monitoring server periodically to not disturb the normal message flow. The Monitoring Server receives events 
from the Agent, optionally filters/handlers events and stores them into a Database.
</section>

</section>

<section><title>Changes</title>
<para>
Not applicable - first publicly released version.
</para>
</section>


<section><title>Fixed Bugs</title>
<para>
Not applicable - first publicly released version.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Known Limitations</title>

<para><emphasis role="strong"> SAM Server only works on Tomcat 6 but not on ESB Server OSGi container</emphasis></para>
<para>In this release of the Talend ESB the Service Activity Management (SAM) Server needs to be deployed on Tomcat 6. 
In future versions of Talend ESB we will also support the deployment within the Talend ESB OSGi container. 
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Known Issues</title>
<para>
Not applicable - first publicly released version.
</para>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Export Notice</title>
<para>
This distribution includes cryptographic software.  The country in which
you currently reside may have restrictions on the import, possession, use,
and/or re-export to another country, of encryption software.  BEFORE using
any encryption software, please check your country's laws, regulations and
policies concerning the import, possession, or use, and re-export of
encryption software, to see if this is permitted.  See
&lt;http://www.wassenaar.org/> for more information. 

The U.S. Government Department of Commerce, Bureau of Industry and Security
(BIS), has classified this software as Export Commodity Control Number
(ECCN) 5D002.C.1, which includes information security software using or
performing cryptographic functions with asymmetric algorithms.  The form
and manner of this Apache Software Foundation distribution makes it eligible
for export under the License Exception ENC Technology Software Unrestricted
(TSU) exception (see the BIS Export Administration Regulations, Section
740.13) for both object code and source code.
</para>
</chapter>

<chapter xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Reporting Defects and Issues</title>
<para>
For community technical support use the Talend
User's Forum at
<link  xlink:href="http://www.talendforge.org/forum/">http://www.talendforge.org/forum/</link> - ‘Talend ESB’. 
You can also look at the Open and Fixed issues provided in the Bug tracker 
<link  xlink:href="https://jira.sopera.de/secure/Dashboard.jspa">https://jira.sopera.de/secure/Dashboard.jspa</link> - Project: Talend ESB
</para>
<para>
If you have a valid customer support contract for Talend ESB (SE/EE) 
with Talend you can access the Talend Online Helpdesk or you can
contact customer support by phone and e-mail as stated in your contracts.
</para>
<para>
Please provide the following information:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
Product and Version which you used (for example, Talend ESB 4.0 SE) 
</listitem><listitem>
Version of Java Platform JDK / JRE in use.
</listitem><listitem>
Log files
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Also, in order to ensure that the technical support team has sufficient information to
help you, describe at least the following in detail:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
your actions up to the point when the problem occurred
</listitem><listitem>
the results you expected
</listitem><listitem>
the ensuing results that differ from your expected results.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</chapter>


</book>
