<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  #%L
  ESB :: Manual
  %%
  Copyright (C) 2011 Talend Inc.
  %%
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  #L%
  -->
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Enabling WS-Security for the Rent a Car demo</title>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose of the STS</title>

    <para>In a heterogeneous environment Web services need to authenticate
    service clients to control their access. When negotiating trust between
    service clients and service providers, an authentication broker can provide
    a common access control infrastructure for a group of applications. For this
    purpose, the authentication broker issues signed security tokens which are
    used by clients to authenticate themselves at the service.</para>

    <para>The STS (Security Token Service) is a service for providing such an
    authentication broker. It issues Security Tokens based on the WS-Trust, a
    standardized specification of Web services based on WS-Security. WS-Trust
    combines two related functions.</para>

    <para>The first function is support for working with security tokens —
    specifically the issuing, renewing, and canceling of security tokens. The
    second function is support for brokering of trust relationships. These two
    functions may seem different, but they interrelate in that security tokens
    require an infrastructure which ensures trust whereever they are handled.</para>

    <para>The core of WS-Trust is a set of messages used to issue, renew,
    cancel, and validate security tokens. Clients calling a SOAP web service
    called Security Token Service (STS) exchange these messages. The tokens
    received as response are used for authentication. They may for instance be transferred
    inside a security header of a request to another service.</para>

    <para>STS implements a simple interface defined by the WS-Trust
    specification. This interface allows clients to use security tokens to
    submit requests for several types of operations. WS-SecurityPolicy can be
    used to specify the types of credentials to be provided by clients or any
    other security processing required on the messages.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advantages of using STS</title>

    <para>For secure communication of a web service and its client a trust
    relationship needs to be established between both.
    If the service and client are in the same security domain, they can have a
    direct trust relationship. In this type of relationship the service and
    client can authenticate each other directly. But if the client and the
    service placed in different security domains they do not have direct trust
    relationship.</para>

    <para>Practically spoken, in a distributed security environment you do not
    want to disclose login credentials and and give access to your user accounts
    to external participants. Thus, you request a certificate-based authentication
    token from the STS server which allows verification of the user authenticity
    at any place where the certificate is known.</para>

    <para>Thus, you can use an STS provider to make trusted connection between
    service consumers and providers without sharing a security domain. STS is
    used to issue a security token, that is a collection of claims such as
    name, role, and authorization code, for the client to access the
    service.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How it works</title>

    <para>The client sends an authentication request with its credentials to the
    STS. The STS verifies the credentials presented by the client and sends
    back a response with a signed security token which certifies that the client
    has authenticated with the STS. The client presents the security token to
    the Web service. The Web service verifies that the token was issued by a
    trusted STS, and on success accepts it in lieu of a successful login.</para>

    <para>The protocol used for issuing security tokens is based on WS-Trust.
    WS-Trust is a Web service specification that builds on WS-Security. It
    describes a protocol used for issuance, exchange, and validation of
    security tokens. WS-Trust provides a solution for interoperability by
    defining a protocol for issuing and exchanging security tokens based on
    the token format.</para>

    <para>In WS-Trust, the type of message sent to an STS to request issuance
    of a security token is known as a Request Security Token (RST) message.
    The RST message contains credentials for the client to be authenticated,
    such as the user ID and password contained in a UsernameToken. The
    response message from the STS is known as a Request Security Token
    Response (RSTR) message. The RSTR contains a security token, such as an
    XML Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) token.</para>

    <para>SAML tokens provide cross-platform interoperability and exchange
    security information between clients and services in different security
    domains. They can be used as part of an interoperability solution allowing
    a client to talk to services running on disparate technologies.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sts_scenario.jpg" format="jpg"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Sample STS scenario:</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>The client sends authentication request to the STS</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The STS validates the client's credentials.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The STS issues a security token to the client.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The client initializes and sends a request message to the
        service which contains the token.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The service validates the security token, and on success processes the
        request.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The service initializes and sends a response message to the
        client.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

	<section>
		<title>Configuring and starting the STS Server</title>
	    <para>In order to enable WS-security for the Rent-a-Car example, the STS
	    server has to be installed and deployed. A sample implementation of the 
		STS server is integrated with the open source technology service framework CXF. 
        </para>
		
	    <para>Use the Maven &quot;pom.xml&quot; file from the directory
	    <code>samples/cxf/sts_issue_operation</code> to build and run STS server.</para>
		<para>Execute either in a UNIX terminal or the Windows command line:</para>
		<para><userinput>mvn clean install</userinput></para>

	    <para>To remove the code generated from the WSDL file and the .class files,
	    run &quot;mvn clean&quot;.</para>
		<para><userinput>mvn clean</userinput></para>
		<para>To run STS server using Maven, enter the following command on a single command line:</para>
        <para><userinput>mvn -Djetty.port=9081 jetty:run</userinput></para>
		<para>This will start a jetty instance on port 9081 and run the STS provider
		configured with this sample Issue operation.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
    <title>Enabling logging on the STS server</title>
	    <para>To enable logging on STS server, add the &quot;org.apache.cxf.feature.LoggingFeature&quot;
	    bean to the endpoint configuration in
	    <code>samples/cxf/sts_issue_operation/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/beans.xml</code>
	    before executing the build using <userinput>mvn clean install</userinput>.</para>
	<programlisting>    &lt;jaxws:endpoint id="SecurityTokenService"
        implementor="#securityTokenServiceProviderBean"
        address="/SecurityTokenService" 
        wsdlLocation="/WEB-INF/wsdl/ws-trust-1.4-service.wsdl"
        xmlns:ns1="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-trust/200512/wsdl"
        serviceName="ns1:SecurityTokenServiceProvider"
        endpointName="ns1:SecurityTokenServiceSOAP"&gt;

        &lt;jaxws:features&gt;
            &lt;bean class="org.apache.cxf.feature.LoggingFeature"/&gt;
        &lt;/jaxws:features&gt;
    &lt;/jaxws:endpoint&gt;
	</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Enabling of WS-Security in the Rent-a-Car example</title>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Build the STS feature.</para>

        <para>Make sure you unpacked talend-esb-4.0-doc.zip and talend-esb-4.0.zip in the same directory.</para>

        <para>Run in Rent-a-Car example root directory: <userinput>mvn clean
        install -Psts</userinput></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Start the STS server on port : 9081</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Configure the default port for the OSGI HTTP Service. In Talend ESB
        container set in file etc\org.ops4j.pax.web.cfg:</para>

        <para><userinput>org.osgi.service.http.port=8080</userinput></para>

        <para>and run container (execute ./container/bin/tesb in the talend-esb-4.0 directory).</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>In the Talend ESB console, type</para>

        <para><userinput>features:addurl
        mvn:org.talend.esb.examples/features/4.0/xml</userinput></para>

        <para><userinput>features:install
        tesb-rac-services-sts</userinput></para>

        <para><userinput>features:install tesb-rac-app-sts</userinput></para>

        <para>Now the STS sample is installed and ready to run.</para>
		
      </step>
	  
	  <step>
	    
		<para>Uninstall STS features.</para>
		 
		<para><userinput>features:uninstall tesb-rac-app-sts</userinput></para>
		 
		<para><userinput>features:uninstall tesb-rac-services-sts</userinput></para>
	  </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration of STS based Authentication in the Rent-a-Car Demo
    example</title>

    <para>Sample STS client and service is configured using CXF.</para>

    <para>For more information about client and service configuration
    read:http://cxf.apache.org/docs/ws-trust.html</para>

    <para>STS CXF client is represented in ../examples/crmservice/client-sts
    folder. STS CXF client configuration located in:
    ../examples/crmservice/client-sts/src/main/resources/META-INF/spring/beans.xml
    file.</para>

    <para>CXF service is represented in
    ../examples/crmservice/service-endpoint-sts. Service configuration is
    located in:
    ../examples/crmservice/service-endpoint-sts/src/main/resources/META-INF/spring/beans.xml
    file.</para>

    <para>Policies and WSDL</para>

    <para>WS-SecureConversation in theory can be used with multiparty message
    exchanges, but the most common usage is for a client communicating with a
    single server. When used in this configuration, the STS that supplies the
    SCT to the client is co-located with the server, accessed at the same
    endpoint address. This means that the web services code on the server
    needs a way to distinguish between messages intended for the STS and those
    intended for the service itself; the action used on the request serves
    that purpose.</para>

    <para>A major part of the WS-Security performance cost comes from the wide
    use of asymmetric encryption. Asymmetric encryption is a useful tool
    because it works with key pairs. Each key in the pair can be used to
    encrypt messages that the other key can decrypt. The owner of a key pair
    can make one key publicly available so that anyone can use it to encrypt
    messages to the owner securely, and also decrypt messages from the owner
    (thereby verifying the sender's identity).</para>

    <para>WS-SecureConversation uses WS-Policy and WS-SecurityPolicy
    configurations that are similar to those used by the basic WS-Security. A
    big difference is that when WS-SecureConversation is used, the policy must
    cover two separate exchanges — that between the client and the STS, and
    that between the client and the actual service. This is handled in the
    policy description by using a nested policy for the exchange with the STS,
    while the main body of the policy applies to the exchange between the
    client and the service.</para>

    <para>Policy configuration of Rent-a-Car STS sample is represented in
    ../examples/crmservice/common/src/main/resources/model/CRMService-sts.wsdl</para>

    <para>For additional information about policies using in CXF please read:
    http://cxf.apache.org/docs/ws-securitypolicy.html and
    http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-securitypolicy/200702/ws-securitypolicy-1.2-spec-
    os.html.</para>

    <para>Keystores and models for the client and service.</para>

    <para>Note that the keys here are not meant for production use--they are
    self-signed and naturally should have passwords different from the
    ones.</para>

    <para>Sample client keystore and configuration for the CRM service is
    located in crmservice\client\src\main\resources\META-INF\spring. It
    contains two files: clientstore.jks and clientKeystore.properties.</para>

    <para>Sample service keystore and configuration for the CRM service is
    located in crmservice\service\src\main\resources\META-INF\spring\. It
    contains two files: servicestore.jks and serviceKeystore.properties.</para>

    <para>For additional information for keystore creation use read Java
    keytool documentation and OpenSSL tutorial: http://www.openssl.org/</para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
